Rick Farouni | Curriculum Vitae

Massachusetts General Hospital/Harvard Medical School

My two main areas of expertise lie in statistical modeling and data science, with a focus on building probabilistic generative models and analyzing large datasets with complex structure. Currently, I am a post-doctoral research fellow in computational biology, working in the lab of Dr. Pinello at the Massachusetts General Hospital/Harvard Medical School. My research projects at the lab involve the application of multivariate statistics, machine learning, and deep learning to epigenomics and CRISPR data. I received a PhD in Quantitative Psychology (statistics applied to modeling psychological and neuroimaging data) and a master's degree in Mathematical Statistics from the Ohio State University.

Experience

Postdoctoral Research Fellow.....

Massachusetts General Hospital/Harvard Medical School

Research Lab of Professor Luca Pinello, Molecular Pathology Unit

MA, USA 06/2017

Research Intern

The Department of Biomedical Informatics Summer Internship Program (BMI SIP)

Research Lab of Professor Ewy Mathè, The Ohio State University

2

Project: Developing an R package and a Shiny app for the analysis of data generated from genome-wide chromatin accessibility assays such as ATAC-seq and DNase-seq with the goal of identifying regulatory elements involved in the cancer epigenetic landscape.

University Teaching Assistant.....

The Ohio State University Graduate Teaching Associate

Ohio, USA

2013–2017

Served as a Teaching Assistant for three courses: Repeated Measures Models, Covariance Structure Models, and Data Analysis in Psychology.

Independent Tutor

Test Preparation Instructor *Instructor of the Graduate Management Admission Test (GMAT)*

Moscow, Russia *2009-2012*

Teacher of English as a Foreign Language

Moscow, Russia 2001-2009

Teacher of General and Academic English

Education

Academic Qualifications.

The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA

PhD in Quantitative Psychology

2015-2017

Dissertation Topic: 'Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States'

The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA

Master of Science in Statistics

2012-2014

The Ohio State University

Ohio, USA

Master's Degree in Quantitative Psychology

2012-2014

Thesis Project: 'Latent Variable Modeling of Categorical Item Responses in a Hierarchical Bayesian Framework'

The Pennsylvania State University

Pennsylvania, USA

Bachelor's Degree in Psychology with High Distinction

2011-2012

Technical Skill Set

Statistics and Machine Learning

- **Scientific Programming Languages:** Proficient in and comfortable transitioning between *R*, *Python* depending on computing goals. Familiar with *Julia*.
- **Deep Learning Frameworks:** Experienced in using Tensorflow and Keras.
- Probabilistic Programming Languages: Proficient in Stan.
- Bioinformatics and Neuroimaging Software
 - Neuroimaging data analysis: Nipype, PyMVPA, FreeSurfer, FSL.
 - Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) data analysis: R's Bioconductor core packages, Bowtie2, MACS2, and bedtools.

Cluster and High-Performance Computing

 Good knowledge of running neuroimaging and bioinformatics analysis pipelines on supercomputing clusters.

Web and Software Development Tools

- LaTeX, Linux OS, Git, Docker, and Bash. Basic knowledge in website development tools such as HTML, CSS, and Jekyll.

Conference Presentations

Joint Statistical Meetings

Seattle

Poster Presentation

2015

Poster Title: Across-Subject Predictive Modeling of fMRI BOLD Responses to Faces using a sparse Bayesian Group Factor Analysis Model

Awards and Fellowships

0	Graduate Student Conference Presentation Award The Ohio State University	2015
0	The Center for Cognitive and Brain Sciences Summer Graduate Fellowship The Ohio State University	2015
	Project Proposal : 'Decoding the Pixels of the Face Image from the Voxels of fMRI BOLD Activity Patterns'	
0	The Social and Behavioral Sciences Summer Fellowship The Ohio State University	2014
0	University Fellowship The Ohio State University	2012

Publications and Software

Journal Papers.....

- o Baskin, E., Farouni, R., and Mathè, E. (2016). ALTRE: workflow for defining ALTered Regulatory Elements using chromatin accessibility data. *Bioinformatics* doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btw688. Preprint available at http://www.biorxiv.org/content/early/2016/10/14/080564.full.pdf+html (first co-author)
- o Pinello, L., Farouni, R., and Yuan, G-C. (2017). Haystack: systematic analysis of the variation of epigenetic states and cell-type specific regulatory elements (under review) doi: 10.1101/199067. Preprint available at https://doi.org/10.1101/199067 (first co-author)

Preprints

Farouni, R. (2017). A Contemporary Overview of Probabilistic Latent Variable Models. arXiv preprint. Preprint available at https://arxiv.org/abs/1706.08137

Dissertation and Thesis

- o Farouni, R. (2017). Application of Deep Latent Generative Models to the Unsupervised Learning of Chromatin States. *PhD Dissertation*. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send_file?accession=osu1492189894812539&disposition=inline
- o Farouni, R. (2014). Latent Variable Models of Categorical Responses in the Bayesian and Frequentist Frameworks. *Masters Thesis*. Manuscript available at https://etd.ohiolink.edu/!etd.send_file?accession=osu1412374136&disposition=inline

Software Development.....

- o ALTRE: A Workflow for Identifying ALTered Regulatory Elements using Chromatin Accessibility Data. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/Mathelab/ALTRE.
- Haystack: systematic analysis of the variation of epigenetic states and cell-type specific regulatory elements. GitHub Repo: https://github.com/pinellolab/haystack_bio.

J	lournal Review Service	
0	Psychometrika Ad Hoc Reviewer	2015
0	Psychological Methods Ad Hoc Reviewer	2016

Personal Details

- Country of Current Residence: USA
- o Country of Previous Residence: Russia (12 years)
- o Marital Status: Married
- o Interests and Hobbies: Evolutionary Biology, World Cuisines, Experimental Music
- o Languages Spoken: English, Arabic, Russian, Spanish (intermediate), French (elementary)